<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Contemplations for the institution of children in the Christian religion. Collected and published by Iohn Carpenter</title>
            <author>Carpenter, John, d. 1621.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18013</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4662</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114418</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849643</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849643</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18013)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1267:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Contemplations for the institution of children in the Christian religion. Collected and published by Iohn Carpenter</title>
                  <author>Carpenter, John, d. 1621.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[100] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By R. R[ead] dwelling in Fleete Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With an errata leaf following F8 verso.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F pi² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catechisms, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Contemplations</hi> For the inſtitution of <hi>Children in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> Religion. Collected and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by <hi>Iohn Carpenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prou. 1.8.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>My ſonne heare thy Fathers doctrine: and forſake not thy mothers Lawe.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London <hi>by</hi> R. R. <hi>dwelling in</hi> Fleete Lane. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:2"/>
            <head>To the right worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Nicholas Wadham</hi> of Meryfield <hi>Eſquire, the grace, mercy and peace</hi> of God the father in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> ❀</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough your worſhips frend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courtiouſnes towardes mee haue ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly merited my grateful minde, as your gentle affablitie with all perſons hath deſerued of them to bee commended: Yet, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how farre (beyond ſome others) I am bound (by reaſon of my cure in <hi>Bra</hi>: where I haue often receiued of your tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall things) to beſtowe on your worſhippe things ſpirituall, the
<pb facs="tcp:14803:3"/>
which, was I might not of duty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, I haue neuer beene vnwilling thankefully to render: I perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded yet more deeplye what to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tate, as wherein I might beſt declare the one and performe the other, or at the leaſt expreſſe a good-will to eyther. But finding that I could not any way elſe ſo well anſwer to the one and ſatiſfie the other in all partes and points, I gladly reſolued to preſent vnto your worſhip this my <hi>Contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> as that which I eſteeme a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent not vnworthy a Right wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull preſence and like accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that in regarde of the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie of the matter, howſoeuer it ſeemeth ſhaddowed vnder my poore Pen. For verily therein (as your worſhip reading the ſame may perceiue) are ſummarily col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and briefly cowched the
<pb facs="tcp:14803:3"/>
principall Grownds of Chriſtian Religion, ſelected and drawne foorth (as certaine ſweet ſtreames) from the pure Fountaine of the moſt ſacred Scriptures, the which not only the moſt Mightie in his Grace and mercy hath both or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, preſerued and commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to his Church: but alſo wee (which are of the houſhould of Faith, and haue the warrant of his ſpirite, which giueth teſtimonie thereof to our ſpirites) doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly beleeue to bee the verye Touch-ſtone whereby the diuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of ſpirites is knowen the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect line, by the which the Temple is meaſured: the rodde whereby a mans wayes are corrected: the Angle with the which the ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Fiſhers vſe to take men: and to be briefe, the Lanterne for our feete, the light to our pathes; and
<pb facs="tcp:14803:4"/>
that bleſſed Table whereon is propoſed to vs in Chriſt, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfull foode of ſoules, whereby men are fed and nouriſhed to life euerlaſting. In regard whereof, as all men are bound to praiſe the high excellencie of that heauenly fountaine, and therein to gloryfie God: ſo am I iuſtly occaſioned to proteſt for the verity and ſweete ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of theſe ſtreames, which in the diuine feare and due regarde of duty, I haue not only thence di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryued: but alſo produced to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes examined and tryed by the authority of the ſame: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do now with the more bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe preſume to preſent vnto your worſhip: praying you to vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe both this my preſent, your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipfull acceptation, and my good will therein, your gentle eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for the which I ſhall be no leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:14803:4"/>
thankefull, then for other your friendly courteſies. And euen thus I commit you with your right worſhipfull Partener to the Almighty.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Norleigh in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uon <date>the 28. Nouem. <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1601.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Worſhips poore Neighbour and perpetuall well-willer. <hi>IOHN CARPENTER.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:5"/>
            <head>Ad Parentes at<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Liberos Hexàſtichon.</head>
            <l>DIſce, parens, púeros pietate ornare tenellos:</l>
            <l>Diſce, puer, verum Relligionis opus.</l>
            <l>Quae doceas, diſcas facili, híc coprênſa labore:</l>
            <l>quae diſcas, doceas, gratus vtér que labor.</l>
            <l>Du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pater et gnátus ſibi múnera debita praeſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</l>
            <l>per ſanctè ſummo ſeruit vtérque Deo.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:5"/>
            <head>To all Children of a Chriſtian towardneſſe: the feare <hi>of God, and eternall health in</hi> Ieſu Chriſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S a certaine Noble and excellent King was neither aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nor greeued to ride ſometimes on a rodde or ſtaffe for the inſtruction of his young Sonne: So neither am I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed or greeued (good Chriſtian children) both to collect and frame for your ſakes, though with ſo ſlender a quill) and like ſtile, as beſt fitting your tender capacitie, certaine Chriſtian In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions, hoping yee will both accept the ſame, and gratefully eſteeme of my good meaning and louing affection
<pb facs="tcp:14803:6"/>
therein expreſſed towards you. But I know well, it will ſeeme very ſtrange vnto ſome, that I haue giuen this my collection the title of Contemplation: for that (after the opinion of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers) contemplation, which is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined either the Godly motion of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine minde: or the diligent and deepe conſideration of heauenly things, doeth not properly appertaine vnto children. Therefore as they placed the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>platiue life, in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>templatiue good, and the contemplatiue felicity in the contemplation of God: ſo the younger ſort (ſay they) haue not (as yet) attained to thoſe three things which are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto neceſſary: that is, <hi>Vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding,</hi> which is an Act of the higheſt power: <hi>Wiſdom</hi> which is the moſt noble ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bite: and <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> which is the worthieſt obiect. Whereof it was, that they reſerued the laſt age of mans life for the conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plation of diuine things, and wold that al the former ages ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:14803:6"/>
be employed on ſome other Sciences, as from the which they might proceede and growe more able in the end to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to the conſideration of things di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine. But thoſe perſons neither begin where Chriſt commaundeth you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne, where he ſayeth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: <hi>Seeke ye firſt the kingdome of God</hi>: nor do they teach, as he teacheth when he ſaith, that <hi>the kingdome of God apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that indeede was no little cauſe that too many (the more pitty) applying themſelues to theſe terrene and worldly things (which <hi>Solomon</hi> worthelie comprehendeth within Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities kingdome) haue moſt vaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſpent out the flower of their youth, and could neuer taſt the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this thing ſo neceſſary and profitable for man in their life, bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed cutte off, and vnhappily
<pb facs="tcp:14803:7"/>
preuented by an vntimely death: for as it is a common thing for men once to dye: ſo neither dooth cruell death ſpare children, of the which too many in thoſe their vaine ſtudies and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh delightes, expect and looke for at the length, but all too late the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie time of ſearching for and enioying thoſe heauenly and profitable exerciſes. Therefore, as it is good for you (deere children) to withſtand ſuch beginnings of miſchiefes, leaſt the medicine for the deſired cure be prepared and applyed too latelie: ſo ought yee to know, that it is not meete yee ſhould conſume the vertues of your minde in the onelye knowledge of thoſe earthly things: but rather to keepe the ſame preſerued for the vſe of things heauenlie and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, the which are euer more profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and neceſſarie in your life; to the which yee are taught and inuited euen by the Lyons and Eagles, which when
<pb facs="tcp:14803:7"/>
when they goe, doe turne their tallents inwarde, to the end they may not weare out, but be preſerued ſharpe and fit for the praye. And ſo ſhould yee likewiſe fill your greene veſſels with that wholſome Water whereof yee ſhould moſt long-ſomly reteine and keepe the ſent and ſauor, to the glorie of God, the benefit of his Church, and your owne health. Neither ought yee ſo much as imagine that the holy Contemplation of diuine things nothing belongeth to young children. Moreouer conſider what is taught you in the ſacred Scriptures: <hi>Solomon</hi> the wifeſt of all the Kings thus counſaileth you: <hi>Remember thy maker in the dayes of thy youth.</hi> And omitting other places, Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaith: <hi>Suffer little Children to come vnto me, and forbid them not. Habel</hi> beeing thus ſchooled by his Parents <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah,</hi> being yet but young, offered vp vnto God a
<pb facs="tcp:14803:8"/>
right acceptable Sacrifice. So <hi>Enoch</hi> in his childhood walked with God, and pleaſed him: ſo <hi>Iſaack</hi> the ſon of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Iſaack,</hi> were religious and godly affected euen in their yong and tender yeares. <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> being a <hi>Nazarite,</hi> was an abſtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner from his birth ſanctified vnto God; <hi>Samuell,</hi> as yet but a little boye, was by <hi>Hannah</hi> his mother brought forth and dedicated to the Lord. Thus alſo both <hi>Dauid,</hi> and <hi>Solomon</hi>: thus <hi>Ioſiah</hi> and <hi>Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Ieremy,</hi> and <hi>Tobiah,</hi> and many others the children of God, whiles they were very young ſauoured of the holy religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Laſtly for a perfect example of your imitation, Chriſt Ieſus being yet but twelue yeares of age exhibited and declared himſelfe moſt learned in the diuine contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, euen in the middeſt of the learned doctors in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Therefore haue I the ſooner, on theſe my briefe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions
<pb facs="tcp:14803:8"/>
impoſed the title of contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation, the ſame being (indeede) god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contemplations, with the which if yee ſhalbe firſt ſeaſoned, yee ſhall (by the grace of God) proſper and proue more able to all vertues in the ſame Ieſus, who beeing the true vnderſtanding, wiſdome, <hi>Immanuell,</hi> is to bee ſought for, imitated and followed of all, aſwell children, as elder perſons, towardes the father Almighty in godly contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore (good Chriſtian chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) vſe you theſe contemplatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s both godly and happily to your natural good, and to the eternall glory of the higheſt <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if it ſhall follow, that this my laboures ſhall be any thing profitable vnto you, by the which the ſooner yee ſhall proſper (through the operation of the bleſsed Spirite) in the right Seruice of God and holye religion,
<pb facs="tcp:14803:9"/>
I ſhall be during my life moſt glad and ioyfull thereof, and I will withall both freelie and thankefully acknowledge that I haue receiued that recompence and reward for thoſe my labours which thereof I might haue expected. And thus fare yee well, and proſper in all Godlineſſe in the Author of our ſaluation, and finiſher of our faith.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>More yours then mine owne in Chriſt Ieſu. IOH: CARPENTER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:9"/>
            <head>Chriſtian <hi>Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations.</hi> ❀</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Childe being called of his father aſketh the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to learne: &amp; his father briefly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth and teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Come hither (my ſonne) and learne of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am here preſent (my father) what will ye, that I ſhould learne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>I would that thou ſhouldeſt learne the feare of the Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that feare of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The feare of the Lord is that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence of God and godlineſſe,<note place="margin">The feare of the Lord. pſal. 111.10. p 10.1.7.</note> wherein God is worſhipped, and the ſame is the beginning of wiſedome.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſt gladly would I be learned in
<pb facs="tcp:14803:10"/>
that feare of the Lord; that thereby I may attaine to wiſedome, therefore I pray you (father) teach me the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The duty of a father and of a ſon.</note> Moſt willingly will I teach thee (my Sonne) that thou maieſt learne: for thus it becommeth me to inſtruct thee: and it is no leſſe thy dutye to learne of me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well then (my father) As I am here preſent before you, harkning vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your wordes of inſtruction: ſo am I ready to learne and obſerue the ſame accordingly: wherefore ſpeake in the name or God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The holy Scriptures are full of good leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> The holye Bible is a plentifull Sea of wholeſome leſſons, of the which I haue choſen one eſpeciall place for the Theme or Argument of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent talke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What haue yee found there writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thus ſaith <hi>Iehouah</hi> to his people the Children of <hi>Iſraell</hi>; conſider this, O <hi>Iacob,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 44.21.</note> and <hi>Iſraell</hi>: for thou art my ſeruaunt. I made thee, that thou ſhouldeſt ſerue me, O thou <hi>Iſraell</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:10"/>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Out of what place of the Scriptures haue yee taken this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
               <p>Out of the propheſie of <hi>Iſayah chap. 44. verſe. 21.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And are thoſe the wordes of God (my father)</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea doubtleſſe (my ſonne (they are the wordes of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſpake God to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>God hath vſed in thoſe tymes to ſpeake unto the people by the happye meanes and Miniſterie of his ſeruants.<note place="margin">How God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>peaketh to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s people.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who are Gods ſeruants</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>God hath many ſeruauntes:<note place="margin">Who are the ſeruants of God.</note> for all the creatures ſerue him in their kinde: but in this he hath vſed the holy Prophets, Apoſtles, Euangeliſts and Martyres.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whome vſeth hee in this time</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The faithfull preachers and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of this word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt wee eſteeme of them and of their wordes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:11"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The eſtie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the miniſter of the word. 1. Cor. 4.1.</note>We muſt eſtéeme of them as of the miniſters of Chriſt and diſpoſers of the Senets of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſpeaketh God to them, and by them to the people.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 10.20.</note>God ſpeaketh to them in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit inſpiring them, which Spirit alſo ſpeaketh in them with the tonge of man vnto the people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then, he that heareth them in this their miniſtery heareth God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and who ſo contemneth them, contemneth God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt rightly ſaid it: as they are the miniſters of Gods word.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus farre I vnderſtand you: but how appertaine theſe wordes to mee, which were ſpoken to the Iſralites.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Prophets wordes to vs.</note> Although they were ſpoken to the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> as chiefly appertaining vnto them: yet do they likewiſe belong vnto all the people of God from whoſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and ſociety I would not thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt be excluded.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who are Gods people Heb. 4.9.</note>
                  <hi>But who are thoſe people of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By this name I vnderſtand all them which doe confeſſe the name of
<pb facs="tcp:14803:11"/>
God, &amp; haue dedicated themſelues who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vnto him, eſpecially the Elected ſons of God new borne in Chriſt by the holy Ghoſt, whom the Lord himſelfe poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth for his owne eternall inheritaunce and choſen lot for euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>So I acknowledge thoſe wordes of the Lord to be both ſpoken to them, and to me likewiſe to appertaine: per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading my ſelfe to be one of that nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and holy ſociety: but what ſhall I learne out of thoſe wordes</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>There be many good things to be learned thereof, and namely foure moſt notable things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the firſt: tell me, I beſeech you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou muſt learne to know thy ſelfe to be made and formed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And that is very needefull to be knowne, what is the ſecond point</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That thou conſider wel who made and formed thée?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And this is no leſſe neceſſary to be knowne then the former: what is the third thing</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That thou know to what end and
<pb facs="tcp:14803:12"/>
purpoſe thou art made and formed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neither indeed ſhould wee bee ignorant thereof if, wee thinke to liue well. What is the foorth thing which is to bee learned out of that text.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
               <p>That thou forget him not which made &amp; formed thee: but that thou inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and remember him with all thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And meete it is wee ſhould ſo doe, els were wee too ingratefull and wicked. But let it pleaſe you that the perticulers bee briefly examined for my better inſtruction</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>With all my heart: for I am moſt willing to teach and reſolue thee in all thinges: and what ſayeſt thou my Sonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>As for the firſt point (my father) what am I taught by this, that I am made or formed</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Thou art taught that thou haſt not this thy béeing and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie of thy ſelfe (as God Allmightye is of himſele) but that thou art made
<pb facs="tcp:14803:12"/>
and formed by the worke and wiſedome of another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is ment by this making or forming.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>The word which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſayah</hi> héere vſeth, noteth, and that not vnaptlye, ſometimes election, ſometimes creation or forming: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times regeneration, redemption, ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and conformation of man to the Image of God, for it is applyed aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well to the Soule, as to the body, and ſo to the whole man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then by this worde, I muſt learne that I am elected, created, rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, redeemed, ſanctified, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Image of God; howbeit, not of my ſelfe, but by the wit and wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of another.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Fa.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and whatſoeuer bleſſings, graces, or benefites elſe thou inioyeſt in this life, or hopeſt to haue in the life to come, they are not of any thine own deſertes, induſtries, ſtudies, power or worthineſſe, but of the grace, goodneſſe, and power of another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then am I vtterly excluded from
<pb facs="tcp:14803:13"/>
all merite or deſert,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Man is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from all merit of goodneſſe.</note> 
                  <hi>hauing in my ſelfe no maner of right of thoſe effects wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I finde not within me the cauſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt ſayde the trueth: and this teacheth thée to be poore in ſpirite, &amp; not to arrogate to thy ſelfe that which is not thine owne: nor to derogate from another that which onely to him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teach me therefore (I pray you) to whome I muſt referre the operation of thoſe good things in me, and aſcribe the praiſes of the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">God is the author of our health.</note> Thou muſt referre all this to him alone who hath ſaid: I made or formed thée: that is to God, to whom onely this thing with the glory thereof belongeth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye haue thus farre right well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed me (my father) and ſeeing this worke and the praiſe thereof muſt bee aſcribed to God, teach me alſo ſomwhat both of the name and of the nature of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The name of god. pſal 82. 1 cor. 8.8. Ioh. 10.32.</note>This word or voyce, God, which we ſo commonly vſe, is not the propper name of the higheſt eſſence: but a name of power, and is common both to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine
<pb facs="tcp:14803:13"/>
Nature, and to all ſuch as haue any lawfull authority and honour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that proper name of God, then</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The proper name of the Deitie is <hi>IEHOVAH:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iehouah.</note> for this beſt fitteth his moſt excellent nature: neither is the ſame rightly attributed to the nature of any thing elſe, or is or may be common to others. This the Iewes called the Name <hi>ineffable:</hi> for that the degrée thereof is excéeding high: and thereof was it, that they ſhould neither write, nor name, nor vſe this moſt holy name in things common or prophane: And therefore the Gréekes alſo according to the number of the letters thereof called it <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the name written with fower letters.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is then a moſt glorious and reuerent Name: but how will yee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The ſignification of this name is taken from that eſſentiall and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all verbe <hi>HAIAH,</hi> and it ſignifieth that one diuine Eſſence or Exiſtence,<note place="margin">He hath beene, or He is.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14803:14"/>
which hath béene from euerlaſting, which is, and which ſhall be without any chaunge foreuer the ſame, of the which all creatures in their creation had and haue their firſt Eſſence, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his moſt frée will, are either kept in béeing, or aboliſhed or chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, who alſo hath declared and wil de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>declare himſelfe ſuch and the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déed and action, the which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and manifeſted himſelfe in his word, wherein he hath ſaid: I wilbe, the which I wilbe. <hi>Exo.2.14.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>There be ſome, who for this word, Iehouah, <hi>do put, Lord, and others put God, in their tranſlations.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is true howbeit, this is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name of God <hi>Iehouah,</hi> for euer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neither by any other word whatſoeuer, can either the diuine Eſſence or his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſignification bee ſo well expreſſed. Therefore, it is to bee wiſhed that this moſt holy name might be onely pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced according to thoſe letters &amp; pointes? in the which the ſame is written in the holy Scriptures, and not ſo tranſlated Lord, or, God, the which wordes indéed ſtand rather amongſt his attributes to
<pb facs="tcp:14803:14"/>
be conſidered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the word) as yee ſaid) was ineffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and not to be pronounced, either among the Iewes or amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Graecians.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It was ſo indéed before the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the moſt holy <hi>Meſſiah</hi>: from and after the which time, the name is both expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and pronounced of all Chriſtians in the reuerend name <hi>Iheſchuh,</hi> or <hi>Ieſus:</hi> which is made of the former name and effable by the interpoſition of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew letter ש wherein is contayned a ſoueraigne miniſtery of godlines.<note place="margin">Tim: 3.16.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And may we not thinke the like of the Hebrew worde Iahh? <hi>for it ſeemeth to ſpring of the ſame roote</hi>?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Indéede we may ſo thinke thereof, not withſtanding this difference is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſed that <hi>Iahh</hi> is a diuinitiue of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah</hi> &amp; ſignifieth God, diminiſhed (as ſpoken vnproperly) that is Ieſus the ſon of God who was abaſed, crucified, and dead in the fleſh: in like ſort as of that ful name <hi>Eloahh,</hi> or <hi>Elohim</hi> is made y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhort voice <hi>El.</hi> which ſignifieth God touching his preſence: as <hi>Iahh</hi> doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his eſſence: And hence was it that in the el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der time the Sonne of God and very
<pb facs="tcp:14803:15"/>
God vſed this word of the futuretence <hi>Ehieh <hi>I wilbe,</hi>
                  </hi> before that he had aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the humane fleſh, that thereby hee might fore ſhew himſelfe to be the ſame which ſhold come: So being made man &amp; conſtituted in his miniſtery &amp; worke of mans redemption, hee ſaith not of himſelfe,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.58.</note> 
                  <hi>I wilbe,</hi> but he ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>I am.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yee haue vttered great and high matters my father, in this miniſtery of Godlines: the Lord giue me wiſdome rightly to vnderſtand the ſame. Now I pray you to ſhew me what thing God is</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>I can much ſooner tell thée what thing God is not: then I am able to ſhew thée what thing God is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſay you ſo my father</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">It cannot be fully ſhewed what thing is God Exo. 25.10. Ezec. 10.</note>Becauſe that as God is without meaſure incomprehenſible, not onely of all men, but alſo of al the bright Angels that ſtand before his face: ſo is it not poſſible that he ſhould be either inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in wordes, or comprehended by hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane meditation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What then ſhould I do in this hard point.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:15"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Séeing that thou maieſt not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him as he is indéede, thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt religiouſly to ſuſpend thy ſearch of him and his moſt high nature incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible: and rather conſider that which God is not: namely his workes: for by this thou maiſt the better vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and conſider what thing God is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What thing is that which I ſhould conſider God is not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That God is neither the earth,<note place="margin">What thing God is not.</note> nor the Sea, nor the heauens, nor the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what ſhould I gather of thet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Séeing thou doubteſt not of the being of God, thou ſhouldeſt lift vp thy minde and heart to that which is yet farre greater and aboue al theſe things</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How will yee define this nature Diuine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>God may better be deſcribed by his attributes and properties,<note place="margin">The Diuine eſſence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> then de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined: howbeit, marke what I ſhall ſay touching this thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In this I am attentiue: proceede therefore (may deere father) &amp; teach me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>When thou heareſt <hi>God</hi> to be na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med,
<pb facs="tcp:14803:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vnderſtand thereby that ſubſtance Inuiſible,<note place="margin">A deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature.</note> vncreate, ſimple, perfect, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible, vnchangeable, immortal, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, incorporall, infinit, the common father, the Lorde and King of althings: the creatour and Gouernour of the world, vnmeaſurable, without place: yea God, which is moſt true, moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, moſt heigh or ſupreme, moſt righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, moſt mercifull, and the Bleſt for euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Surely, yee haue vttered many great matters in few wordes: Now, is it lawfull for me to examine thoſe Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes and properties of the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ty, for mine owne better vnderſtanding.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſtian modeſtie.</note> Chriſtian modeſty will not vrge too far in ſuch heigh matters, leaſt par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture the heigh excellencie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of iuſtly confound ſuch as too curyouſly ſéeke to comprehend that which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comprehenſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yee ſay well (my father) neither will I preſumptiouſly aduenture that, but in the feare of that diuine nature, haue I ſaid that which is ſaid.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and in this bee thou well
<pb facs="tcp:14803:16"/>
aduiſe (my ſonne) that thou ſpeake no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing raſhly, eyther of God,<note place="margin">How to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God.</note> or before him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I will be well wary thereof. But why is God ſayde to bee a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he is ſo indéede:<note place="margin">God is a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note> for were hée not a Subſtance, hee were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all: for that is ſayd to bée a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, which hath his Eſſence or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is hee ſayde to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſible.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he is a ſpirite,<note place="margin">God is inui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible.</note> that is a Spirituall Eſſence. Neyther can wee behold his fulneſſe with the eyes of ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our body, or our minde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hath not this eſſence ſometimes appeared vnto men</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Men are not capable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: therefore, albeit that God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in ſome kinde of formes eyther in dreames, or in the day time to men: yet hath his Eſſence béene euer hidden from their ſight.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sonne.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore is God called
<pb facs="tcp:14803:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
vncreate</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe God is alwayes the ſame, creating all things,<note place="margin">God is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>create.</note> not made, nor crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelfe: the beginning or ending of whoſe age canot be remembred.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is he called ſimple</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Simple.</note> For that he is manifeſtly true, without foulding, circumſtances and wembes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Perfect.</note>
                  <hi>Wherefore is he ſaid to be perfect.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>For that he is abſolutely vpright, firme, and hath knoweth and worketh althings perfectly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is he ſaid to be incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Incompre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible.</note> It is certaine, that neither the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of God, nor his eſſence, nor his counſels nor his workes, can of vs be comprehended: yea, and he dwelleth in that light which is acceſſible. <hi>1. Tim. 6.16. Pſal.145.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And why call ye him mutable</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vnchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> For that he cannot by any meanes be changed from that which he is: and for that neither anger, wrath, repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce: forgetfullneſſe, recordation nor any ſuch like, can properly fall into the
<pb facs="tcp:14803:17"/>
nature diuine: nor in his eternitie, nor in his veritie, nor in his will: is there any thing changeable. To be briefe, béeing immortall, eternall, and true, neither his nature, nor his béeing, can at any time by any meanes periſh or decay.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhy is he called eternall?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By the ſame reaſon that hée is without beginning aſwell touching the time, as the cauſe and thing:<note place="margin">Eternall.</note> he is eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, for he is wholy life, and the life can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be death:<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.9.</note> therfore neyther was there any time, or any other imagined ſpace before time, in the which God was not, or liued not.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhy is he called immortall?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Immortall.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>For that as he had no beginning, ſo neyther ſhall he haue ending, liuing the ſame for euer</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhy is he incorporall?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Incorporall.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>For that he is an inuiſible ſpirite,<note place="margin">Ioh. 4 Act. 7.24. Iſa. 60.</note> not compact of any bodily lineaments, nor is conteyned in any certayne place.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVherefore is he called infinite?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Infinite</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He is without limits,<note place="margin">Heb. 4.13. Ier. 23.24. Amos. 9.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Iſay. 66.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery where. Wherefore from him there is nothing hidden: but he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:14803:18"/>
all things, béeing abſent from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: he is all in heauen, he is all in earth: he is diffuſed through, and in all, and euery thing, yea comprehending and working all and euery particuler thing whatſoeuer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore is he the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon father.</note> For that he is a benefactor not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his choſen: but alſo to other men, &amp; to all creatures: yea, truly, as he is the Creator,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.9. Pſal. 36.6. 1. cor. 8.6. Epheſ. 4.6. Mat. 5.4. pſal. 1.47. gen. 33.11.</note> the ſuſteiner, the conſeruer, and the nouriſher of all things: howbeit, he is eſpecially the father of his elect in his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhy call ye God, the Lord and king of all things</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Lord and king of all Iſay. 45.9. 1. tim. 6.15. Iam. 2 19.</note>Becauſe he is full of maieſtie, by the which he aſtoniſheth all creatures, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the rule in all things, and the ſame, to whom the knée of euery thing boweth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S,</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And wherefore is he named the Creator and gouernour of the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>For that the ſame God omnipotent, the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt, one and three, that is to ſay: one in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and three in perſon: hath both cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated
<pb facs="tcp:14803:18"/>
heauen and earth,<note place="margin">Creator and gouernor of the world. gen. 1.1. act. 17.14.</note> and formed all things in the ſame, the which alſo he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneth wiſely for euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why do ye call him vnmeaſurable?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>For that neyther his quantity,<note place="margin">Without meaſure. act. 7.48.</note> nor his quality, can be meaſured by any of his creatures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhy is he ſayd to be without place</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he paſſeth not from one place to another:<note place="margin">Illocall</note> neither may he be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in places, for he filleth all places:<note place="margin">àct. 7.49. 2. chro. 6.18.</note> in that he is ſayd ſometimes to be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, or to go, or to dwell, or to be contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this or that place: it is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtoode not touching his nature or eſſence: but of his graces, vertues, operation and effectes in his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moreouer, I remember that in the deſcription of God: ye ſayde that he is moſt true, moſt mightie, moſt high or ſupreme, moſt righteous, moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and the beſt of all for euer. And vvhy ſayde you ſo? I pray you teach mee</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He is indéede <hi>Moſt true:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">God is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> true,</note> for he is
<pb facs="tcp:14803:19"/>
moſt faythfull,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5. 2. Tim. 13.</note> ſéeing he is for euer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable, both in his nature, in his truth, in his will, and in his euerlaſtingneſſe: whereof it is that he performeth and perfecteth whatſoeuer he promiſeth or threatneth:<note place="margin">Heb. 10.13.</note> neyther is it poſſible that God ſhould lye.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Moſt mighty</note> He is moſt mightie, yea omnipotent: for he hath all the powers,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.14.</note> &amp; habilitie of executing, performing, and effecting all things,<note place="margin">Ioh. 16.2.</note> not of us, nor any other of his creatures,<note place="margin">Mat. 19.26.</note> but of himſelfe, and nothing vnto him is impoſſible to be done.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Moſt high.</note> He is <hi>Moſt high or ſupreame,</hi> for wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> he diuelleth in the heauens,<note place="margin">Gen. 14. Pſal. 73. &amp;. 77. &amp;. 91.</note> and in reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of Angels and men, as of all other creatures, he is in the higheſt degrée, dignitie, and glory, ſubiect to nothing, gréeued with no paſſions, and whoſe eſſence, name, glory, and kingdome, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth all humane vnderſtanding.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Moſt righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</p>
                     <p>1. Sam. 16.17 Iſay. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.16. gen. 18.</p>
                     <p>Moſt merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ll. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 36:7. Ro. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.3. 2. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </note>He is <hi>moſt righteous</hi>: both in himſelfe and in the execution of his iudgements.</p>
               <p>He is <hi>moſt mercifull:</hi> not onely to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes his choſen people, but alſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes all, although not after one ſorte: to his choſen for their health: to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate
<pb facs="tcp:14803:19"/>
in this life for their greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, of their owne deſert:<note place="margin">Moſt patient. Pſal. 86.7. Ro. 9.22. 2. pet. 3.9.</note> and as he is moſt mercifull; ſo is he moſt pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent euen towards the veſſel of his wrath</p>
               <p>Laſtly, God is <hi>the beſt foreuer,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt foreuer.</note> for why? he is moſt holy: and this is no leſſe true, if he reſpect eyther God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe or all his worke, for aſwell in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as in al his workes he is the <hi>Beſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay. 6.3 mat. 19.17. Apo. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.1. Eze. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.12.</note> and whatſoeuer things are holy, the ſame hath God ſanctified: and being the <hi>Beſt,</hi> he is the giuer of all good things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>All theſe things haue ye well taught me: what elſe remayneth for me to be learned my father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Now (my ſoone) I will that thou conſider well thrée eſpecial good things,<note place="margin">3. things to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red."</note> which are of the promiſes to be gathered.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat are thoſe things?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The firſt is, that God is that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine nature which is not created: but the ſame which hath created all things whatſoeuer. The next is, that God is that chiefe good thing, aboue the which there is nothing. The third is, that God is the ſame, the which the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of man acknowledgeth to be the
<pb facs="tcp:14803:20"/>
chiefeſt,<note place="margin">rom. 11.36.</note> the greateſt, the moſt perfect, and infinite, of whom, in whom, and by whom, are all things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I haue by theſe wordes conceiued much more in minde, then my mouth is able to vtter</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>But I ſhall approach yet more neare to their vnderſtanding, when I ſhall tell thee how this diuine nature is diſtinguiſhed into certayne perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Plurality of perſons in the deitie.</note>
                  <hi>And are there more then one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the deitie</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Year: and this hath béene taught vs not onely by that God himſelfe is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times heard to ſpeak in the plural num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, but alſo by that word <hi>Elohim,</hi> which is interpreted God, beſides other au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities and teſtimonies in the holy Scriptures.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhere is God heard to ſpeake in that ſorte?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In the booke of the creation, <hi>Chap. 2.26.</hi> God ſayd, <hi>Let vs make man, in our image, after our likneſſe.</hi> Agayne, <hi>Chap. 3.22. <hi>This man</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith God) <hi>hath beene as one of vs.</hi> Againe, <hi>Chap. 11.7. <hi>Come on</hi>
                  </hi> (ſayth God) <hi>Let vs go downe, &amp; there
<pb facs="tcp:14803:20"/>
confound their language.</hi> In the which maner of ſpeaking, is noted the plurali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of perſons in the Godheade.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That ſeemeth manifeſt indeed, but how gather ye this of Elohim?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Elohim</hi> is one of the names of God, and a worde of the plurall number: by the which muſt be underſtoode the pluralitie of perſons: howbeit, to note the vnitie of conſent and ioynt operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe perſons, it taketh a Verbe or Pronoune of the ſinguler number.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where finde ye that my father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In the very beginning of that booke of the creation, it is ſayd by <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">gen. 1.1.</note> that <hi>Elohim</hi> created the heauens and the earth: where we finde that <hi>Elohim</hi> is of the plurall, and the worde <hi>Created</hi> of the ſinguler number.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yee haue well ſayd: but then how many perſons haue ye found to be in the Godhead?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>I haue found three perſons in the godhead:<note place="margin">Three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in the godhead.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which alſo hath béen rightly gathered by the moſt ancient doctors of the church, of the very letters of the moſt holy name <hi>IEHOVAH,</hi> beſides
<pb facs="tcp:14803:21"/>
many other pregnant teſtimonies in the worde of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declare me the reaſon thereof I pray you?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By the firſt letter of that name, which is <hi>IOD,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">IOD.</note> and is the number of tenne which noteth perfection, is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the firſt perſon: by the ſecond let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>HE,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">HE.</note> which ſignifieth the Eſſence, is vnderſtode the ſecond perſon, by whom indéede all the creatures haue their Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and béeing, and by the doubling of the ſame letter is noted a double nature, namely the diuine &amp; humane in the ſame perſon inſeperable: by the third letter which is <hi>VAV,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">VAV.</note> a copulatiue, is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the third perſon, béeing that ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Ardour and loue betwéene that firſt and ſecond perſon: and of this triplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of perſons, the Godhead is called the Trinitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</note>
                  <hi>Then the Trinity is the name of the Dietie or Godhead, as the ſame is diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed or conſidered in three perſons?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and there withall as we may underſtand him in his diuers and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry properties and workings euen here
<pb facs="tcp:14803:21"/>
in the worlde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is he named in the firſt perſon of the Trinitie?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Firſt perſon.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F</speaker>
               <p>God the Father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is he called in the ſecond perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Second per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>God the Sonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is the third perſon named?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>God the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the Father is God, the Sonne is God, and the holy Ghoſt is God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt therein well ſayd.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But are there not then three Gods?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo: but one God in Eſſence,<note place="margin">One God.</note> the which is neyther diuided, nor ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, though the Godhead be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed into three diſtinct perſons.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then ye would that I ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Trinitie in Vnitie.</note> 
                  <hi>three to be in one, and one to be in three: that is, three perſons in one di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine Eſſence, and one diuine Eſſence in three perſons?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea truly, and that in this Trinitie there is the Father, and the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt: but in the vnitie onely one God, and the ſame foreuer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I like well of your plaine maner of teaching wherof I haue taken no meane
<pb facs="tcp:14803:22"/>
inſtruction and comfort. Now tell me father (I beſeech you) how God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">God is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</note> Although God be the common fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the creator, the author, the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and the ſuſteyner of all things: yet here he is called a father in reſpect of the ſonne, whom he hath begotten before all worldes, very God of very God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is he called the ſonne?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">God the Sonne.</note> He is called the ſonne in two re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: firſt, as hauing a relation to the father of whom he was begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with whom, he is coeſſentiall, coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall, and coeternall. Secondly, in that he became man, and was borne of the virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ſonne was made a perfect man</note>
                  <hi>And was the ſonne a perfect man, as he was a perfect God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, for as he is perfect God of the ſubſtance of God his father: ſo is he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect man of the ſubſtance of the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> his mother.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>So then ye ſay that he had a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule, as he had a humane bodie: for this neceſſarily followeth.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea for as a perfect man conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:14803:22"/>
both of a humane body, and a reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſoule: ſo thou muſt beléeue that this ſecond perſon in the Trinitie had not onely ſuch a bodie, but alſo ſuch a ſoule, as he was man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And was that his diuine nature, combined with his humane nature in this perſon?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea doubtleſſe,<note place="margin">The god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head and manhood conioyned in one Chriſt.</note> and thereof béeing God and man, he became one Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVho was his mother, as he is God: and who was his father, as he is man?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Is he is God he hath no mother: and as he is man he hath no father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And yet he hath both father and mother, muſt I not beleeue ſo</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>Yes: for as he is Chriſt, he hath God his Father in heauen, and the Virgin his Mother on earth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How then was he begotten, as he was man</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Of the holy ſpirite, inſpiring the holy virgin, without the knowledge of any man. <hi>Luke <hi>1.</hi>35.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>This is a wonderfull conception?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:23"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>So is it indeede: howbeit with God it was nothing impoſſible.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The holy Ghoſt.</note>
                  <hi>How is God called the holy ſpirite?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Not onely in that he is that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Eſſence: but alſo in that he powreth foorth of his vertues and graces, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is ſayd to procéede from the father and the ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that holy ſpirite then?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That diuine perſon in the Trinitie which procéedeth from the father and the ſonne, to whom, and with whom, he he is both coeternall and coeſſenciall, which repleniſheth the faythfull with all good things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then this I learne, that the father is the firſt perſon in the diuine Trinitie, not made, nor created: The ſonne is the ſecond perſon begotten of the father: the holy Ghoſt is the third perſon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from the father and the ſonne?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſayeſt well, and it is needefull that thou thus beléeue, as touching the Trinitie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat do you diſtinctly attribute to thoſe three diſtinct perſons?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Although that neither the Godhead
<pb facs="tcp:14803:23"/>
is diuided nor the perſons ſeperated in ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or working,<note place="margin">Diſtinct o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perations of the three diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</note> howſoeuer they be diſtinguiſhed: yet to euery one of thoſe perſons is attributed a proper worke, in and for the good of the choſen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that which is properly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributed to God the father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Election and creation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is there attributed to the ſon?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Redemption, iuſtification, &amp; ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat may we attribute to the holy Ghoſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Illumination, regeneration, and ſanctification.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that which ye call election?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Election.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Election</hi> is that diuine choyſe and ſure mercie of God, whereby before he made the world, he did foreknow them whom he wold glorifie, that they might ſtand before him without blame, and become his adopted children through Chriſt, according to the good pleaſure of his owne will. <hi>Ephe. 1.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVas there no good thing then in man, which God foreſaw to merite or deſerue this choyſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Nothing at all: for whatſoeuer he
<pb facs="tcp:14803:24"/>
did therein,<note place="margin">God elected his, of his own accord, and that freely.</note> was of his owne accorde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And is not man able to deſerue for this</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Never, albeit he ſhould liue tenne thouſand yeares, neyther (indeede) dath God expect it: for God elected him of his owne will, ſo he elected him fréely, knowing well that man could neuer be of power to requite him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then we haue no merite where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to challenge heauen, or to iuſtifie our ſelues before God</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>None at all, therefore we are ſaid to be ſeruants vnprofitable, and ſinners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of man before God</note>
                  <hi>By whom are we accepted and iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified then</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By Chriſt Ieſus our Lord, who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them, whom the father had known before and choſen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Creation.</note>
                  <hi>Ye attributed alſo to God the worke of creation, what hath God cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated and of what matter hath he created, the ſame</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>God hath created heauen and earth: yea, and that of no former matter: for to create is properly to make ſomething of nothing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:24"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then, ſo in them hath God crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea and he hath made and formed thee.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of what matter hath he made mee</hi>?<note place="margin">The matter whereof man was made.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>As touching thy body, of the duſt of the earth: as touching thy ſoule, of the breath of life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat thing was I then made</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>A liuing ſoule.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In whoſe image was I formed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In the Image of God. <hi>Gen. 1.27<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat Image is that; for God is a ſpirite.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Wiſdome, holineſſe, righteouſnes,<note place="margin">The image of God.</note> and all perfection.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now what ſay ye of the proper of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the ſonne.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The proper office of Chriſt.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>As God the father elected and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: ſo the ſonne redéemeth, iuſtifieth, and ſaueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that which ye call re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">redemption.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The recouering agayne, buying &amp; fréeing of that which was ſold, the price thereof béeing paied: ſo he redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
<pb facs="tcp:14803:25"/>
mankinde is the recouering, fréeing and taking home agayne of mankinde from the bondage of hell, death, and the diuel, his ranſome béeing payed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How was man ſold away into that miſerie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Through his owne ſinne and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion agaynſt the law of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The malice of the diuel.</note>
                  <hi>Who moued him to that rebellion?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The Diuel by his ſubtill temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How did the Diuell tempt him</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He abuſed the bodie of the ſerpent in whom he ſpake, &amp; thereby beguiled firſt <hi>Heuah,</hi> and afterward <hi>Adam. Gen. 3.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But what is that to all other men?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of ſin.</note> So effectuall, that through <hi>Adam</hi> they be all dead, infected with this here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary maladie, grafted in the nature of man to his deſtruction, and eternall damnation, were it not that Chriſt hath redéemed them whom his father had choſen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The price of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  <hi>VVith what ranſome did Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme me</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Not with gold or ſiluer, or ny ſuch like thing, but with his owne precious bloud, as of a Lambe vndefiled and
<pb facs="tcp:14803:25"/>
without ſpot.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But thinke ye this ranſome was ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to redeeme all the Lords elect.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea doubtleſſe it is ſufficient for them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How then was this applied to them of the olde Teſtament</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By the mercie of God who enabled them to beléeue in Chriſt then to come,<note place="margin">The Fathers of the old teſtament.</note> as we now beléeue in him béeing paſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then the effect of his death was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended as well to them as to vs?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, &amp; therefore he is called a lambe, ſlayne from the beginning of the world, to be an effectuall ſacrifice for all the elect.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And is not the death of Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient and effectuall vnto all?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>We may not derogate from the death of Chriſt any thing of the ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encie or effect thereof, for the ſame is both ſufficient and effectuall vnto all: though not to all alike.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teach me this more plainely</hi>?<note place="margin">The ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacie of Chriſtes death to all.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The death of Chriſt is ſufficient and of power to redéeme all, if al haue grace with fayth to apprehend his righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes:
<pb facs="tcp:14803:26"/>
&amp; his death is not onely effectuall to the choſen of the Lord to redáeeme them: but alſo to the diuels, reprobates, and all the powers of darkeneſſe, and children of perdition, to condemne, confound, and vtterly to deſtroy them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue I learned (my father) how the ſon of God hath redeemed me: what ſay ye of Iuſtification, the which ye did alſo properly attribute to Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iuſtification.</note> Iuſtification is that approbation of a man before God the father.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherof conſiſteth this Iuſtification.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Of the remiſſion and putting away of ſinnes, and of the imputation of the righteouſneſſe and innocencie of Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is this applied vnto me</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is applied vnto tháe of the méere loue, and mercie of God in his ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt I apprehend the ſame?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By fayth onely, which is the hand of the ſoule, to accept ſuch a benefit.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Chriſt is made ours.</note>
                  <hi>How hath he wrought this righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe for me?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He ſatiſfied for thy ſinne<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued death, by his owne death: hee iuſtified thée which had no merite, by
<pb facs="tcp:14803:26"/>
his owne iuſtice, the which he declared in his reſurrection from the deade. <hi>Act. 13.38.39.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What profit haue we by this?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>F.</hi> As he was eſtéemed a ſinner in that he bare our ſinnes:<note place="margin">The vſe of our iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> ſo are we eſtéemed righteous by the imputation of his righteouſneſſe vnto vs: and as he died for our tranſgreſſions: ſo doe we liue here and for euer through his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then is he no leſſe worthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Sauiour, to whom ye alſo aſcribed the ſaluation of ſoules?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Saluation.</note> and thereof is he rightly called <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as he is both God and man: neither is there any other name vnder the heauens, in whom, or by whom we be ſaued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is ſignified by the name Ieſus?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ieſus a Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That he is a Sauiour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhom hath he ſaued?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>His people.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVho be they</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame whom the father hath choſen before, and are rightly called the
<pb facs="tcp:14803:27"/>
people of God as I ſayd before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>From what doth he ſaue them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>From ſin and the reward thereof.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What ſin iſ.</note>
                  <hi>What is that which ye call ſinne</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That is called ſinne, whatſoeuer is not according to the law of God, and thereof be two ſortes, namely, originall and actuall ſinne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that originall ſinne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Originall.</note> Originall ſinne is that hereditarie deſeaſe which is deſcended from <hi>Adam,</hi> as namely the ignorance of the minde, the concupiſcence of the fleſh, and the want of originall righteouſneſſe: in the which ſinne, a man is borne the childe of wrath, and cannot poſſibly pleaſe God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that actuall ſinne</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Actuall.</note> Actuall ſinne is that what ſoeuer a man either thinketh, or ſpeaketh, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth agaynſt the law of God, &amp; agaynſt his owne conſcience.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhereof commeth this ſinne?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This ſin procéedeth of the corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of man, &amp; is an effect of the former.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the rewarde of ſinne</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The reward of ſinne.</note> The reward of ſinne is death, not onely of the body, but of the ſoule alſo, which is called eternall damnation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:27"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then from this hath the ſonne of God ſaued his people, and therefore is worthely named Ieſus our ſauiour: but ſhew me alſo I pray you, why is he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He is called Chriſt,<note place="margin">What the name Chriſt ſignifieth.</note> becauſe he is the holy anointed of <hi>Iehouah</hi> before al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reſt,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>With what oyle is he anoynted?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>With the oyle of gladneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The Vertue of the holy ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To what dignitie, function, or office was he anoynted with this oyle</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>To be a king, a prieſt and a prophet.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein is he a king?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Not onely in that he is the very king and Lord of heauen and earth:<note place="margin">Chriſt is our King.</note> but alſo in that he hath to himſelfe indued al the powers of darkenes, from the which he hath reduced vs, and with his great powre doth gouerne and ſuſteine vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein is he our prieſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In that he hath not onely offered vp himſelfe to God for vs,<note place="margin">He is our Prieſt.</note> but alſo ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth at the right hand of the father ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king interceſſion for our health.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein is he our Prophet.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In that he hath both reuealed vnto vs
<pb facs="tcp:14803:28"/>
the diuine miſteries, and alſo that hee might dired vs the way to life, hath hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pely gone before vs towardes the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then worthely is he called a redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, a iuſtifier, and a ſauiour: but by whom am I drawne vnto him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs to Chriſt. Ioh.</note> By God the father: for no man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to Chriſt, but ſuch whom the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther draweth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doth God the father draw me to Chriſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Ierm. 31.3.</note>By his mercy he draweth thée vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And is there any cauſe in man that moueth God to this mercie?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>None at all, but that which God doth in this, he doth it of his owne loue in his ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein doth god expreſſe this mercy.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In many and great things: and here in the ordinarie calling of a chriſtian: for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he predeſtinated, them alſo he called.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the calling of a Chriſtian?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The calling of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> It is that whereby he is inuited to the kingdome of Chriſt, fayth, remiſſion of ſinnes, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, and to a new life, and life euerlaſting.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How then am I called</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:28"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>God béeing merciful vnto thée, allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth thée externally by his worde prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and inwardly by the motion of his ſpirite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Are both theſe, namely the outward &amp; inward calling neceſſary for a chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea, and therefore we ought not to neglect the one, nor contemne the other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus farre haue you diſputed in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der touching the ſonne: howbeit one thing remayneth yet doubtfull (my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) the which I would gladly ye ſhould diſcuſſe</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>What is that (my ſonne.)</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye ſaid, that the father, the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt are one thing, and that the diuine Nature cannot eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be diuided: and yet, that neither the father nor the holy Ghoſt was made fleſh, but the ſonne onely, which alſo was the alone redeemer of mankinde:<note place="margin">Not the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nor the holy Ghoſt was incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate but the ſonne. Auguſt de incarna cohu. Iudaeos.</note> how (I pray you) may this be</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Let him reſolue this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who hath for an example thereof ſo elegantly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced the harmonie of a muſicall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument: conſider (ſayth hée) the muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal inſtrument, as it yéeldeth the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical ſound: therein, thrée things ſéeme to
<pb facs="tcp:14803:29"/>
be preſent together, as namely, the arte or cunning, the hand, and the corde: the arte doeth ſuggerate, or indite: the hand ſtriketh, and the corde ſoundeth, three here worke together, yet onely the corde ſoundeth: neyther the arte nor the hand yéeldeth ſound, but then only when they worke together with the corde: euen ſo, neyther the father, nor the holy ghoſt hath taken fleſh, yet haue both wrought together with the ſonne: the corde onely yéeldeth the ſound: Chriſt onely hath béene incarnate. The operation conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all the three: but as the yéelding of the ſound appertayneth onely to the corde, ſo the taking of fleſh, appertay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth onely to Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye haue excellently reſolued me in this doubt, and ſo haue ſufficiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed me touching the ſonne the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond perſon of the diuine Trinitie. Now at length I remember, that to the third perſon, ye attributed illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, regeneration, and ſanctification.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The workes of the holy Ghoſt.</note> It is true, for theſe three things are proper to the holy ghoſt, albeit that in the ſame, the whole Trinitie hath his
<pb facs="tcp:14803:29"/>
operation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What meane ye by this illuminatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Illuminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Illumination, as it is generally ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, noteth ſometimes the new birth, ſometimes the viuification, ſometimes the fréedome, ſometimes the iuſtification of a man: but in this place, by Illumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is meant that lightning of reaſon and iudgement wrougth in the faithfull by the diuine vertue, whereby the eyes of the ſoule béeing opened, they both ſée God, and learne to walke in his waies.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then it appeareth that ſometimes they haue beene darkened in their vnderſtanding, and know not at all how to order themſelues</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is moſt certaine, &amp; thereof did men runne into ſo many groſſe errours in the world, as a puniſhment for their ſinnes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Right needefull then was it, that Chriſt after his departure from his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples, ſent the holy Ghoſt vnto them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt ſayd the truth, for by the vertue thereof they were lightned, and led into all trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is this holy ſpirit ſayd to be giuen or receiued.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:30"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt is ſaid to be giuen.</note> As concerning his graces, vertues operations, and effects: for otherwiſe, being God incomprehenſible, and reple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing al things he is neither giuen nor taken, nor ſaid properly to remoue, to go, or to come from one place to another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye alſo attributed to the holy ghoſt regeneration? what meane ye by that.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Regeneration is of that, which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendred againe, or new borne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Shew me this more plainely</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Euery man is ſpiritually dead, by reaſon of ſin, therefore it is néedeful that he be reduced to that Image of God, which is in him defaced, by a new birth, and hereof is he made a new man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The old man</note>
                  <hi>VVhat is the olde man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is the fleſhlie man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVho is that fleſhlie man.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is he which is not indued with the ſpirit of God, but by nature without the holy ſpirit: which is alſo called the <hi>outward man:</hi> that is he, which conſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of the body and the ſences, which is giuen to affections, and is mortall. The ſame is alſo called the <hi>body of ſin,</hi> that is a body ſubdued to ſinne, fleſh, ſenſuall, and earthly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:30"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that new man</hi>?<note place="margin">The new man.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is that ſpirituall man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVho is he.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The man inſpired with the graces of gods ſpirit whereof he is a new crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and ſpirit, or the <hi>ſpirituall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man</hi>: that is one regenerated by the worke of the holy ghoſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> very ſoule and the image of God, which through faith and grace doth flouriſh euen in the middeſt of afflictions, neither may he be by any meanes extinguiſhed: to this alſo belongeth the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond man:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ro. 5.8. 1. cor. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> is that firſt, Chriſt is that ſecond: the firſt is terrene or earthly, the ſecond is celeſtiall or heauenly.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doth the holy Ghoſt worke this in vs.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He conuerteth vs vnto God, confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vs to the image of his ſonne, in the renewing of our mindes: the which in the ſcriptures is often vnderſtood in the worde <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>It was not then for nought, that both God and his prophets in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Chriſt and his apoſtles in the new, haue ſo often excited and called the people to repentance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:31"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Well ſayde, neither without this can a man enter into the kingdome of heauen. <hi>Io. 3.5.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What oportunitie taketh the holy ghoſt in the working of this regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The hearing of the worde of God, whereof fayth is engendred in the hart of man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye alſo attributed (as I remember) to the holy ſpirit, ſanctification: and what is that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> Sanctification is the purifying of a man from all prophanitie: the cleanſing of a man, by the mortificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the fleſh, and the confirmation, and application of vs to God, by the viuification of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the which (indeede) is the end of our deliuerance from hell, death, &amp; the diuell.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue I learned what are the chiefe attributes or properties of thoſe three diſtinct perſons in the diuine Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: now what remayneth els for me to learne (my good father?)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What God requireth of vs.</note> Yea, thou haſt hard what <hi>Iehouah</hi> hath done for thée. Now alſo muſt thou learne what he requireth thée to yéelde vnto him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:31"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what is that (my good father.)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Repeate the Theme or argument of our talke, &amp; thou ſhalt therby know it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I made thee (ſaith Iehouah) <hi>that thou ſhouldeſt be my ſeruant: therefore, thou</hi> Iſraell, <hi>forget me not?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Well then:<note place="margin">The end of our creation &amp; redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</note> to what end did <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah</hi> make thée? aunſwere me to the wordes of our Theme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That I ſhould ſerue him (as I take it) and that I ſhould not forget him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou haſt ſayd the truth, and this is the end of creation, redemption, and regeneration.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is ment by this worde ſeruice</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The worde generally noteth that condition of a man, whereby he liueth vnder the will and rule of another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that ye call Gods ſeruice</hi>?<note place="margin">God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Seruice of God</hi> is no ſeruile condition, but that diuine worſhippe and true execution and performance of thoſe good workes which are preſcribed and commaunded to be done in the worde of God, and namely, in thoſe two ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles of the lawe, wherein are briefely contayned the <hi>Tenne Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:14803:32"/>
of Almightie God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what are thoſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame which God ſpake, and are written in the <hi>20.</hi> chapter of the ſecond booke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> which is called <hi>Exodus.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I beſeech you my father, to recite them all vnto me in order.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Then hearken (my ſonne:) God ſpake all theſe wordes ſaying.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <note place="margin">The tenne commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of God.</note>
                  <hi>1</hi> I am <hi>Iehouah</hi> thy God, which haue brought thée out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> land of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> from the houſe of bondage: thou ſhalt haue no ſtrange Gods before me.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <hi>2</hi> Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, nor the ſimilitude of any thing, that is either in heauen aboue, or in the earth beneath, or in the water vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the earth: thou ſhalt not adore them, nor worſhip them: for I <hi>Iehouah</hi> thy God am a iealous God,<note place="margin">The firſt Table.</note> viſiting the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities of the fathers vpon the children, in the third and fourth generation of them which hate me: and ſhewing mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie to thouſands of them that loue me, and keepe my commaundements.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <hi>3</hi> Thou ſhalt not take the name of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houah</hi> thy God in vayne, for <hi>Iehouah</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14803:32"/>
will not hold him guiltleſſe that taketh his name in vayne.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <hi>4</hi> Remember the Saboth day, that thou ſanctifie it, ſix dayes ſhalt thou labour, and do all thy worke: but in the ſeauenth day is the Saboth of <hi>Iehouah</hi> thy God, in it, thou ſhalt not do any worke, thou and thy ſonne, and thy daughter, thy manſeruant, and thy maideſeruant, thy cattell, and the ſtranger that is within thy gates: for in ſix dayes <hi>Iehouah</hi> made heauen and earth, the ſea, and all that in them is, and reſted the ſeauenth day: and therefore <hi>Iehouah</hi> bleſſed the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth day and hallowed it.</p>
               <p>Theſe foure commandements are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in the firſt table: the ſix that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low are of the ſecond table.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <hi>5</hi> Honor thy father and thy mother that thy dayes may be prolonged in the land which <hi>Iehouah</hi> thy God giueth thée.<note place="margin">The ſecond Table.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="6">
                  <hi>6</hi> Thou ſhalt not kill.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <hi>7</hi> Thou ſhall not commit adultrie.</p>
               <p n="8">
                  <hi>8</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <hi>9</hi> Thou ſhalt not beare falſe witneſſe agaynſt thy neighbour.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <hi>10</hi> Thou ſhalt not couet thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb facs="tcp:14803:33"/>
houſe: thou ſhalt not couet thy neighbours wife, or his ſeruant, or his maide, or his oxe or his aſſe, or any thing that is thy neighbours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Summe of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note>
                  <hi>How many things doe theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements generally concerne</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Two things: firſt thy dutie towards God: next thy dutie towards thy neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye haue ſufficiently taught me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the nature &amp; eſſence of God. Now briefely in the way, I beſeech you to ſhew me who is my neighbour?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Who is my neighbour.</note> Generally, all men borne of <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah</hi> are thy neighbours: but chiefely they which are of the familie of fayth be thy neighbours: for all which are of the ſame familie are alſo of the ſame bodie in Chriſt, and coheires of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which of thoſe commaundementes do concerne my dutie towards God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe foure which are contayned in the firſt table.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which doe concerne my dutie to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes my neighbour?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe ſixe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſecond table.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:33"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherein are thoſe commandements perfected.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In loue,<note place="margin">The perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the law.</note> namely that thou loue God and thy neighbour.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt I loue God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhalt loue <hi>Iehouah</hi> thy God with al thy hart, and with al thy minde,<note place="margin">Loue God.</note> and with all thy ſtrength, and with all thy thought.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt I loue my neighbour?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thou ſhalt loue thy neighbour as thy ſelfe.<note place="margin">Loue thy neighbour:</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Howbeit it ſeemeth vnto me, that ſome of thoſe commaundements do not preſcribe vnto vs any ſinguler worke, but onely do forbid the doing of ſome certayne things?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Here thou muſt obſerue (my ſonne) that thoſe commandements wherein we are forbidden that which is euill,<note place="margin">In thoſe commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, wherein we are forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the euil, we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to doe the good.</note> we are commanded to do the contrarie, that is, that we do that thing which is good: and that in thoſe other commandements, whereby we be commanded to doe thoſe works which are good &amp; honeſt, we are forbidden to do the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, that is, ſuch works as be vngodly and diſhoneſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I pray you teach me this matter
<pb facs="tcp:14803:34"/>
more playnely?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Muſt gladly, howbeit, aſke of me &amp; I will certifie thée of all things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The firſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note>
                  <hi>Go to then firſt God hath ſaid I am Iehouah <hi>thy God &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> what hath God commaunded herein?</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth that we ſhould take and eſtéeme him the onely <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah</hi> for our God: next that we ſhould not feigne vnto our ſelues any ſtrange gods.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 2.</note>
                  <hi>VVhat commaundeth he in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond commaundement</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt he forbiddeth all idolatrie and feigned worſhippe: ſecondly that thou worſhip him, and ſerue him onely, not in the likeneſſe of any forme, but in ſpirit and truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 3.</note>
                  <hi>VVhat commaundeth he in the third commaundement?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In this he commaundeth thée to abſtayne from al vaine oathes, and from the prophane abuſe of the name of God: moreouer he teacheth thée to call on, and to ſweare by his name, with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, and in the feare of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The 4.</note>
                  <hi>What willeth he in the fourth</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt that ſixe dayes thou ſhalt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour in the worke of thy vocation: next
<pb facs="tcp:14803:34"/>
that thou preſume not on the ſeauenth day to do any ſeruile labour: but that thou kéepe holy the ſeauenth day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What hath he enioyned me in the fift commaundement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The 5.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That thou honour &amp; obey thy parents aſwell ſpirituall as bodily, with loue, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, modeſtie, feare, and dutie: and on the other ſide, that thou diſhonour them not, nor vnreuerently abuſe them, nor in any ſorte neglect them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What hath God preſcribed me in the ſixt?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The 6.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That thou kill not any man in thought, worde or déede: next, that thou thinke well of thy neighbour, and report him well: and that thou endeauour to profit all perſons, and reléeue them, and preſerue the life of them to thy power.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What commandeth he in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth commaundement tell me</hi>?<note place="margin">The 7.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, he commaundeth thée to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from all fleſhly luſtes and vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body: ſecondly, that thou walke honeſtly and ſoberly in this life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſaieth he in the eight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The 8.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:35"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, he forbiddeth thée to take away from thy neighbour by ſtealth, or any vnlawfull meanes, eyther his externall good &amp; poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or his good name, fame, and reputation: Next he biddeth thée to expreſſe and exerciſe towards they neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the vertues of liberalitie, aimes, déedes, and mercie, according to thy power, and that thou be beneficiall to him, his goodes, and fame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ninth.</note>
                  <hi>What is preſcribed me in the nynth comaundement.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt, thou art therein forbidden al lying, periuries, back bitings, contume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, brawlings, contentions, and flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: next, that thou reporte well of thy neighbour, and that thou teſtifie, and ſpeake the truth of him in all things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The ten commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente.</note>
                  <hi>What biddeth he in the tenth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That thou do not ſo much as couet that which is an others: ſecondly, that thou endeauour that euery one may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne his owne, yea, and rather to wiſh him ſome part of that which is thine, then vniuſtly to deſire that which is his.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue ye fully ſatiſfied me in this poynt. But is a man able of himſelfe
<pb facs="tcp:14803:35"/>
to obſerue and performe theſe comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of Almightie God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By no meanes, and yet this not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,<note place="margin">Man is not able to fufill theſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note> the Lord hath in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie ordeyned man a meane the ſame to performe, after his good pleaſure.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that meane; (my father)</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſt is the perfection and end of the law.</note> in whom the father is very well pleaſed, and in, and by whom, all ſuch as beléeue in him doe kéepe and performe the whole: for he is both the perfection and end of the law.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many things requireth he of vs therby.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Two things, wherof the one is <hi>faith,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Faith and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.</note> the other is <hi>obedience,</hi> in the which alſo is contayned the ſumme of religion, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther without theſe two things can any one of theſe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dements be obſerued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Which of theſe two things doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlye proceede, &amp; go before the other.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fayth</hi> goeth before, <hi>obedience</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth after, <hi>fayth</hi> is at the roote, <hi>obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> is as the fruit: <hi>faith</hi> is as the cauſe, <hi>obedience</hi> as the effect: the one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, the other performeth: and this latter is a teſtimonie of the former, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing that in worde and déede, which
<pb facs="tcp:14803:36"/>
was in beléeuing conceiued in the hart by the operation of the holy ghoſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What thing is that which ye call faith?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What faith is.</note>
                  <hi>Faith</hi> is defined to be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which maketh thoſe things to be, which are hoped for, &amp; demonſtrateth that which is not ſéene.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What kinde of faith is there requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in this ſeruice of God</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That which is called the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Liuely faith:</hi> the ſame which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the true Chriſtians and fruitfull in godly vertues.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what is that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is the gift of God engendred in the ſoule of the ſpirite of God, by the preaching of the word: and is defined a firme opinion,<note place="margin">Chriſtian faith.</note> and conſtant conſcience of righteouſnes, and ſaluation, obtayned by none other meanes but onely by the frée mercie of God in his ſonne.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are the things which are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obiected to this faith?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of faith.</note> Thoſe things which here follow in order, as firſt God that diuine nature in the vnitie: next the ſame God in the Trinitie: thirdly the holy Catholicke Church: and laſtly all thoſe Articles of the Chriſtian faith, whereof we muſt
<pb facs="tcp:14803:36"/>
not doubt, but be abſolutely and certein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aſſured in our beliefe,</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What are thoſe Articles of beliefe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The ſame which are comprehended vnder the title of the ſimbole of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: that is.</p>
               <p>I beléeue in <hi>God the father almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> marker of heauen and earth,<note place="margin">The Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bole of the Apoſtles.</note> and in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> his onely ſonne our Lord, which was conceiued by the holy ghoſt: borne of the virgin Mary: ſuffered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Pontius Pilate: was crucified, dead and buried, he deſcended into hell: the third day he roſe agayne from the dead: he aſcending into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the father al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie: from thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the deade. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeue in the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> I beléeue the <hi>holy Catholick church,</hi> the <hi>Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſaintes</hi> the <hi>forgiueneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> the <hi>reſurrection of the bodie,</hi> and <hi>the life euerlaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Muſt I the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beleeue in al theſe things?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">To bleeue 1. that God is. 2. that whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God ſaith. 3. In G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is néedfull, that thou beléeue all theſe things to be, but it is not requiſite that thou beléeue in them all.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Seeing therefore that this particle
<pb facs="tcp:14803:37"/>
(In) maketh ſuch a difference, in what thing then muſt I beleeue</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Beleeue in the holy Trinitie.</note> In that <hi>holy Trinitie,</hi> namely in God the father, in God the ſonne and in God the holy ghoſt, which is in nature one thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And what muſt I beleeue with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this particle. In?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Beleeue the holy Church. &amp;c.</note> The holy Catholicke church, &amp; thoſe other things contained in the Articles which folow in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſimbole, to be true.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye haue before this ſufficiently taught me, to knowe the former obicte of my fayth, namely God in the trinitie, and the Trinitie in the Vnitie: nowe I pray you to declare vnto me thoſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter pointes: and firſt what is that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke church, which yee would that I ſhould conſtantly beleeue</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What this Church is.</note> By this church is meant the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall companie, or faythfull aſſembly of Gods people, of the which ſome hauing paſſed the troubles of this life, are with Chriſt in heauen, and other ſome (as yet) are millitant on the earth, where in the vnitie of the true doctrine, and the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vſe of the Sacraments, they cleaue together.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:37"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that communion of ſaints?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Sainte</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The fellowſhippe, familiaritie, and amitie, that the godly haue one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in one fayth, one hope, one charity, as children of one father in one houſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing mutuall beneficience, works of mercie &amp; chriſtian duties,<note place="margin">The forgiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſins.</note> one towardes another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that forgiuenes of ſinnes the which I muſt alſo beleeue?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is the looſing and releaſing of that band of obligation, wherein we be tyed to eternall death and damnation: yea, and a pardon of that payne which our ſins had deſerued, and that by the onely death &amp; merit of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat muſt I beleeue touching the Reſurrection of the fleſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The reſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the fleſh.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That in the laſt day, all men ſhall riſe agayne with their bodies: the godly to eternal life: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wicked to eternal paine.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that eternall life?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That bleſſed felicitie and happie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which the elected ſaints ſhall haue and enioy after their reſurrection from death in all eternitie,<note place="margin">The life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting:</note> with Chriſt the ſonne of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue ye taught me (my good
<pb facs="tcp:14803:38"/>
father) what this Chriſtian fayth is, and what, and wherin I muſt beleeue: now let me know alſo how this Fayth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by hearing of Gods word.</note> As faith is a frée gift of God, as I ſaid before: ſo God will, that this fayth ſhould come by hearing, and namely of the worde of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is that wrought?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By the operation of the holy ghoſt, which engendreth faith right happely in the hart of him, who is a fruitfull hearer of the <hi>worde of God.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">What is that word of God.</note>
                  <hi>VVhat is that which ye call the worde of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F</speaker>
               <p>By the <hi>worde of God,</hi> in this place is vnderſtoode the <hi>holy ſcriptures,</hi> both of the old &amp; new Teſtaments, the which with many ſtrong arguments doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate the will and workes of God, and eſpecially thoſe promiſes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne the redéemer, and eternall life, for thoſe ſcriptures we call the <hi>worde of God,</hi> which béeing comfortable, happie, effectuall, &amp; ſufficient to man, doth both inſtruct him in his dutie in this life, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo derect him to that <hi>euerlaſting word of God,</hi> which was w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god before al worlds.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:38"/>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt this worde be vnto me applied?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By the miniſtrie of the preachers,<note place="margin">How this word is to be applyed vnto vs.</note> and miniſters of the ſame.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who be the preachers and miniſters of this worde</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thoſe parſons,<note place="margin">The Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers and miniſters of the word.</note> whom the Lord ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth foorth furniſhed with méete gifts &amp; lawfully called into the church, which chiefly regard to celebrate, to praiſe, &amp; to commend with feuencie of ſpirit, &amp; that openly before all men, the name of God, and the worde of his grace, &amp; the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What ſhal I do whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is not a prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, nor a meete miniſter of the word?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt thou muſt pray the Lord of the harueſt to ſend foorth labourers into his harueſt: then,<note place="margin">What is to be done there where the paſtor is abſent.</note> it is meete that thou read both dilligently, &amp; reuerently, the worde of God, and meditate therein with a pure minde euery day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat if I cannot reade?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It behoueth thée to repayre to them that can reade, and inſtruct thée concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning God, and thy duty towards him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt this worde be preached and read.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:39"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How this word is to be preached and heard.</note> Faythfully, diſtinctly, diſcréetely, wholy, diligently, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly &amp; reuerently.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt this worde be heard?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>With faith, diligence, reuerence, feare of the Lord, and harty deſire to learne it, to vnderſtand it, and to reforme this life thereby.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue ye taught me the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary meanes to obtayne faith: now tell me alſo how this faith is confirmed</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How faith is conformed. Ioh. 4.</note>There was a time when that <hi>faith</hi> which came by hearing, was confirmed by miracles, and workes of wonder.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In what time was it confirmed</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In the time of Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and in the primitiue church: and néedfull it was then, when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth of the Goſpell began to be publiſhed the which béeing now ſufficiently confirmed vnto vs, miracles are no longer néedfull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherby is faith co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed in vs now</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sacraments.</note>Euen in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exerciſe of the ſame word by the which it was begon, but chiefely in the true vſe of the Sacraments.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may I beter vnderſtand this.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>As the Sacraments themſelues are the ſeales of Gods promiſes made to vs: ſo the right vſe of them ratifieth in vs
<pb facs="tcp:14803:39"/>
that faith by the which we apprehend that which is promiſed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that which ye cal a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi>?<note place="margin">What is a Sacrament</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Not only the ſeale of thoſe things of which God hath promiſed vs (as I haue before ſayd) but alſo an externall ſigne of ſome internall vertue or grace.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhereof is a Sacrament made</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Of theſe two things,<note place="margin">Whereof a ſacrament is made.</note> namely the <hi>worde of God,</hi> and the <hi>Element.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhereunto ſerueth the worde</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>To the eare in the lawfull miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie thereof, and to the inward man by the operation of the diuine ſpirite.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVherunto ſerueth the Element</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>To the eye, the faſt, the féeling, and eternall man: for as a man is of two na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, namely of the ſoule and body, of the ſpirite and fleſh: ſo is he of the grace &amp; mercie of god, edified in either of them.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many Sacraments be there in chriſtian vſe</hi>?<note place="margin">There be two <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>acra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Two, which are called Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the new Teſtament.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat are thoſe two</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Babtiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Supper of the Lord,</hi> both the which are alſo ſignified in that water, and bloud which iſſued from
<pb facs="tcp:14803:40"/>
the ſide of Chriſt on the croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Baptiſme.</note>
                  <hi>What is that ſacrament of Baptiſme.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This ſacrament of baptiſme or waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, is diuerſly defined, for it is ſaid to be either the badge of regeneration into a new life,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.</note> and eternall health, or the ſigne of our purgation in Chriſts bloud: or the ſcale of the promiſe of remiſſion of ſinnes, in the name of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Baptiſme.</note>
                  <hi>What is the Element whereunto the word adioineth to make this ſacrament.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Water which waſheth onely the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die without.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is the inward grace which is therein ſignified.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The cleanſing of vs from our ſins.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And are they throughly cleanſed which are waſhed in that water.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>No, for that inward waſhing com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not of that worke wrought, but of the holy ghoſt in the faythfull, which vſe this element as a ſimbole of this waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and not as the cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who inſtituted and commaunded this to be done and vſed in the church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> who hath promiſed life vnto them which beléeue, and be baptiſed, and hath threatned
<pb facs="tcp:14803:40"/>
death to them which beléeue not.<note place="margin">Mat. 16.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that ſacrament of the Lords ſupper</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The <hi>Supper of the Lord</hi> is a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall banquet,<note place="margin">The Lordes Supper.</note> whereby Chriſt witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth himſelfe to be the bread of life, by the which our ſoules are fed to the true imortalitie of the ſoule: or it is an holy Simbole or ſigne, wherein Chriſt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and communicateth his body and bloud thereby to certifie vs of the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſinnes, and life euerlaſting or, it is the happy memoriall of the death of Chriſt; and an whoalſome and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſigne of that Sacrifice which hée made once for all on the Altar of the croſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is the outward Element of this ſacrament?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The eleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Bread and wine, which féedeth and cheareth the bodie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is the inward grace, which is ſignified thereby, and giuen to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy receiuers thereof</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The body and bloud of Chriſt, by the which we are nouriſhed and chea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to eternall life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue I hapely learned how ſaith
<pb facs="tcp:14803:41"/>
is conformed in me: Now alſo would I gladly learne, how the ſame is encreaſed.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How faith is increaſed.</note> This faith which commeth by hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and is confirmed in the vſe of the Sacraments, is alſo happely encreaſed by godly cogitations and meditations, but chiefly by good conference and talke of thoſe things which the worde doth both ſuggerate and teach vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">With whom we muſt talke</note>
                  <hi>With whom muſt I confer &amp; talke?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>With the learned, godly, and ſuch as feare God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of what thing muſt we talke</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Of God, of Gods worde, of the kingdome of heauen.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How muſt I confer thereof.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">In what ſort we ought to talke of thoſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note> Not arrogantly as they vſe to do, which endeauour to maintaine vaine ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and friuolous queſtions, but with all reuerence, ſobrietie, wiſdome, and the feare of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How faith is fructified.</note>
                  <hi>How is this faith fructified and made fruitfull both in my ſelfe and others</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Partly by godly examples: partly by deuout praier &amp; religious meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whoſe examples muſt I place before me to be followed</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The holy examples of the faithfull,
<pb facs="tcp:14803:41"/>
whom it behoueth thée to follow, and thereby alſo to exhibit thy ſelfe an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of godlineſſe vnto others.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How is fayth fructified by prayer?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In thy ſelfe, as fayth is furthered, ſtrengthened, and made frutefull in thy hart: in others, as fayth is ſtrengthened and propagated in them, by thine holy life and religion, to the glory of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus haue ye right wel inſtructed me in the one part of that ſeruice which God requireth: namely faith: now what ſay ye of the ſecond point</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>The ſecond part of this ſeruice is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience.<note place="margin">Obedience what it is.</note>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that which ye cal obedience?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Obedience is that ſubmiſſion of the minde, whereby a man yéeldeth himſelfe to the worde &amp; will of him that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, and doth without any contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on performe the ſame to his powre: obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towards God is that ſubmiſſion, whereby the faithfull minde gladly yéel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth himſelfe to the word and will of God: and this is that new obedience, which otherwiſe is called the fruit of righteouſneſſe, or good works comaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the certaine and expreſſe worde
<pb facs="tcp:14803:42"/>
of God, wrought in them that be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated by the helpe of Gods ſpirit, faith ſhining in their harts, to this end, that therein God may be glorified, and our neighbour benefited, and they are the teſtimonies of a true fayth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where are theſe works to be learned</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In that written word of God, wherin they are preſcribed, is for our learning.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then haue I throughly learned wherein this ſeruice of God conſiſteth: Now teach me alſo the maner of this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice I beſeech you my father?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">How we muſt ſerue God.</note> God béeing a ſpirit will be ſerued in ſpirite and truth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How may that be?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>In holineſſe and righteouſneſſe, euen before him without feare all the dayes of thy life.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Declare this more plainly I pray you?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It behooveth thée to ſerue God pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe he is pure: iuſtly, becauſe he is iuſt: that is with a faythfull hart, and ſound life, that not onely before men, but alſo before God himſelfe, and that not doubtingly, nor negligently: but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly &amp; continually vnto thy liues end.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And is a man able in this ſort to ſerue God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:42"/>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>He hath not of himſelfe any power ſo to do:<note place="margin">A man hath not the pow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er to ſerue God &amp; yet may well ſerue him by faith.</note> and yet is it poſſible that he may ſerue him.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How can that be?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By that liuely fayth, whereby it pleaſeth Chriſt to imparte vnto man his righteouſneſſe and ſufficiencie, and thereby granteth him to walke in his vocation.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But ſeeing I haue none habilitie of my ſelfe, but that which enableth me muſt come from Chriſt? by what meanes ſhall I obtayne it?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>By a good faith (as I haue before ſaid) but ſo that as faith is ſtrengthened and fructified by praier: ſo is obedience by inuoca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And doth the Lord command this to be done?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44. Forget me not.</note> and the ſame we finde among other things included within this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement. <hi>Forget me not.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How many things requireth the Lord by this?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Two, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt wherof is this, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, his goodnes towards vs, &amp; our duty towards him, we ſhould neither ingrat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully forget y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one, nor negligently omit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14803:43"/>
other,<note place="margin">To be thankfull to God.</note> but alwayes gratefully remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his goodneſſe, and ſerue him in our liues, in holynes and righteouſneſſe: the ſecond is,<note place="margin">To craue helpe of God.</note> that we deſire of him aide, and things neceſſary for vs, for the ſake of Chriſt our ſauiour: and theſe two points are contayned in deuout prayer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that prayer?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prayer what it is.</note> It is a part of diuine addoration, wherin we haue both conuerſation and familiar talke with God. Or it is the ſame whereby the godly minde is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnto God, with a certaine humble and ſpirituall affection: (or according to the words of our theme) it is the ſame, whereby the faithfull minde is humblie and feruently powred foorth vnto God, either in praiſing him for his benefits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or in crauing of him thoſe good things which are thought neceſſary for vs.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>To whom ought we to pray?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To whome we muſt pray.</note> To God in the Trinitie &amp; in the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie: to God I ſay, which is thrée &amp; one.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And may we turne our ſelues to none other in praier?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>No indéed, for in ſo doing we derogate from the Lord that which to him is due:
<pb facs="tcp:14803:43"/>
and giue it vniuſtly to another.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat forme of prayer hath hee preſcribed me?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>That which Chriſt hath appointed vs for an example,<note place="margin">The forme of a Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> prayer.</note> and hath commnded his Apoſtles and diſciples with all dilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to obſerue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Teach me to know that forme of praier?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>When ye pray (ſaid our Lord Chriſt vnto them) ſay yée.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father which art in heauen,<note place="margin">The Lordes prayer.</note> hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy name: thy kingdome come: thy will be done in earth, as it is in heauen: giue vs this day our dayly bread: and forgiue vs our treſſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe agaynſt vs: and leade vs not into temptation: but deliuer vs from euill, for thine is the kingdome, the power, and the glory, for euer. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat do we in this prayer</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">The Sum of this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</note> we lift vp our mindes to God with whome we haue familiar talke.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, we call, and reuerently ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him, for our heauenly father.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, we confeſſe his higheſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie and power.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Fourthly, we prayſe and glorifie his
<pb facs="tcp:14803:44"/>
moſt holy name.</p>
               <p n="5">5 Fiftly, we deſire the encreaſe of his ſupreame kingdome euery where, both in our ſelues and others.</p>
               <p n="6">6 Sixtly, we relie wholy on his good will, and pleaſure.</p>
               <p n="7">7 Seauenthly, we craue of him ſuch things as we want in this world, both in bodie and ſoule.</p>
               <p n="8">8 Eightly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> we humbly deſire pardon of al our ſinnes, as we are ready to pardon them that offend agaynſt vs.</p>
               <p n="9">9 Ninthly, we beſéeth him not to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer vs ouer into the hands of our dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enemie the Diuell, but to deliuer vs from his tyrannie.</p>
               <p n="10">10 Tenthly, we adde the reaſon that moueth vs to run vnto him with theſe our petitions, the which is rightly taken from the conſideration of his dominion, might, and high glory: and for the rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication &amp; confirmation of all the which, we ſay in the place of a concluſion and of the aſſent to the ſame, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is ſignified by Amen?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Amen, what the word ſignifieth.</note> It is ſo much to ſay, as <hi>So be it:</hi> let it be ratified and faithfully effected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, which ſayd voyce (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may yet
<pb facs="tcp:14803:44"/>
more plainely expreſſe the emhpaſis and force therof, according to the Hebrewes, is formed of the firſt letters of thrée ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall wordes, whereof the firſt letter, namely <hi>A:</hi> is taken from the word <hi>A L</hi> which is interpreted God:<note place="margin">God.</note> the ſecond letter that is <hi>M,</hi> is borrowed of the word <hi>Melech,</hi> which is a king:<note place="margin">King.</note> the third letter béeing <hi>Nun,</hi> is the firſt letter of <hi>Neeman,</hi> which is ſo much to ſay as <hi>faithfull,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Faithfull.</note> and <hi>true</hi>: Therefore of thoſe thrée letters <hi>A M N</hi> is gathered that voice <hi>Amen:</hi> which is as much to ſay, as <hi>God, the King, Faythfull and true.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O very well ſayde (my father) and thus haue yee right well taught me to what end the Lord hath formed me, and hath made me a liuing ſoule, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored me to his owne image?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Yea (my ſonne) and in thoſe two poyntes, namely fayth and obedience,<note place="margin">The ſum of religion.</note> I haue taught thée the ſumme of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And (I beſeech you) teach me alſo what that Religion is?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Father.</speaker>
               <p>True Religion is that ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, combination, and league of ours,<note place="margin">True relig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:14803:45"/>
with the true, liuing, and eternall God in the vnitie, and trinitie, whom onely (béeing vnto him in Chriſt conioyned) we do adore, inuocate, and worſhip, on whom we wholy depend, according to whoſe will, or after the preſcript and law of whoſe word, we liue in al things.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus are we formed to ſerue God, and to liue in his holy religion: but what is the end of this ſeruice? and what profit ſhall we finde thereby?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Two prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall of Gods ſeruice.</note> This ſeruice hath two principall ends: the firſt whereof is the glory of the euerlaſting God: the ſecond is the profit and benefit of man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that glory of God?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>As glory is the publick and often praiſe of good report of any perſon, ſo the glory of God, is the preaching of his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble acts and vertues, the extolling &amp; ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth of his name, with high praiſe and thankeſgiuing: and this is the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall end both of mans life and death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Then alſo ſhould a man wholy liue and die to glorifie God</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is true, ſo long therfore as a man may in his life expreſſe and ſpread foorth the glory of God: ſo long let him deſire
<pb facs="tcp:14803:45"/>
to liue, and not to die:<note place="margin">How long a man ſhould diſire to liue.</note> but when he can no longer performe that, but rather to glorifie God in his death, let him deſire rather to dye, then to liue.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>Ye haue well ſayd (my father) God graunt we may both liue and die to his glorie. Now, I pray, let me heare the reaſon of that ſecond poynt, the which (as ye ſayd) reſpected mans profit and benefit?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>Thy labours in the Lord ſhal not be in vaine,<note place="margin">The reward of Gods ſeruice</note> for through the merit of the moſt holy <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wrath of God which was enkindled agaynſt thée, by the meanes of ſinne, ſhall be remoued far from thée: the graces of God ſhall be eſtabliſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thée: thy conſcience ſhall be quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted within thée: thou ſhalt finde preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and ſafetie agaynſt all thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, both bodily and ghoſtly: thou ſhalt not come into condemnation: thou ſhalt not fall into the death eternall: and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, thou ſhalt enioy the higheſt felicitie in the life to come.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that wrath of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gods wrath.</note> 
                  <hi>the which ye ſay ſhall be remoued?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>This wrath is not to be eſtéemed for any perturbation of minde in God, but
<pb facs="tcp:14803:46"/>
for the payne of the ſufferer,<note place="margin">Lam. 3.10.</note> béeing the worthy reuenge of ſinne. The wrath of God therefore is the retrebution of ſins, which is ſayd to be two wayes, that is ſay,<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.</note> either then when he puniſheth the ſinner for his amendment: or then when he caſteth him into hell fire to be deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for euer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that grace of God where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ye alſo made mention</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Gods grace.</note> The grace of God, is his louing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour and good will towardes vs, by the which béeing mercifull, he doth affect vs wretched and damned ſinners, while he pardoneth both the payne and the fault of our tranſgreſſions, and adopteth vs for his children: or it is that remiſſion of ſinnes, or mercie promiſed for the ſake of Chriſt our ſauiour: or our frée acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God, the which the holy ghoſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paneth for our eternal good.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I haue thus far wel vnderſtood you, what is that good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience ye ſpeak of.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">A good conſience.</note> As conſcience generally is defined, the knowledge, iudgement, and ſence of man, wherby his minde béeing acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery thing that hath by himſelfe béene done or not done, he doth either co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne or cleare himſelfe, &amp; ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth vnto
<pb facs="tcp:14803:46"/>
him inſtead of a <hi>1000.</hi> witneſſes: ſo a good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience is the ſpiritual face of the ſoule, the candle of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minde, the incorruptible iudge, and braſen wall, &amp; impenitrable, euer abſoluing him which reteineth it through the only mercy of Gob, &amp; defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him againſt al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtroks of ſin &amp; death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that preſeruation of man</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is that ſafe kéeping,<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of a man</note> by the which the Lord doth preſerue and nouriſh both the ſoules and bodies of the righteous, to the which he giueth his angels charge to kéepe them in al their wayes through the merit of their redéemer.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVhat is that condemnation</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is that moſt dreadfull ſentence,<note place="margin">Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</note> the which Chriſt the moſt righteous iudge ſhall pronounce agaynſt the reprobate, diuell &amp; his wicked angels in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vhat is that eternall death</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is that final ſeperatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man form Chriſt,<note place="margin">Death eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</note> whereby he may not thence forth enioy his preſence: this is the ſecond death, which is the confuſion and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truction of both ſoule and bodie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of enſueth a perpetual horrour of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence conceiued of the diuine wrath.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that higheſt felicitie of man</hi>?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>It is that euerlaſting life, whereof I
<pb facs="tcp:14803:47"/>
ſpeake before,<note place="margin">Mans heigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt felicity.</note> the which after this life we that be true beléeuers ſhall enioy with Chriſt, and all his choſen ſaints in the moſt bleſſed peace, and happie ſocietie for euermore.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>S.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Now (my good father) as ye haue beene willing to teach &amp; nurture me in the right feare of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The cocluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
                  <hi>which is the beginning of wiſdome (as ye haue ſayd) ſo well diſcuſſed al thoſe doubts, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfied me at full, ſo wil I both endeauor to retaine in minde, what ſo euerye haue taught me: and alſo continue right thankfull vnto you, for all thoſe your godly leſſons, inſtitutions, and contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plations, and there withall aſcribe vnto our beſt and higheſt God, the praiſe and glory due to his moſt holy name?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>F.</speaker>
               <p>So be it: and thus that moſt good &amp; ſupreme God, bleſſe thée (my ſonne) and grant thée the right wiſdome and grace, to liue proſperouſly in thy vocation after his will, to the comfort of thy parents &amp; friends, to the good of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth, to the diſcharge of thy duty, and to his praiſe &amp; glory, who hath made &amp; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med thée to ſerue him, through his deare ſonne our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </sp>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:47"/>
            <head>A godly prayer for <hi>Children to vſe.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Almightie God, and our moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Father; we thy deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (béeing taugth by thy worde (doe know the nature of thy goodneſſe to be ſuch, that as thou art alwayes ready to giue, glad to forgiue, &amp; willing to bleſſe and proſper them, that appertaine vnto thée: ſo thy will and pleaſure is, that we ſhold learne thy lawes, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end we may know how to glorifie thée, &amp; walke in thy wayes: and that becauſe there is no man able to performe this without the aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of thy ſpirit, thou haſt promiſed to ſend foorth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame vnto them that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deſire, and runne vnto thée: now therefore (O good father) we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging our faults, &amp; our vnworthineſſe, do come vnto thée &amp; proſtrate our ſelues before thy footſtoole, in the hope and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of thy te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der mercies: to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould the childe come, but vnto his father? and to whom ſhould we come but vnto thée? for howſoeuer we haue faulted agaynſt heauen, and agaynſt thée, and are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to be called thy ſonnes: yet art
<pb facs="tcp:14803:48"/>
thou our father, and we hope that in the name of thy moſt deare ſon Ieſus, thou wilt not denie vs to be thy children. Let it be thy good pleaſure (O father) to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don all our defects and ignorances, to looke on vs in thy loue, to imbrace vs with thy fauour, and to bleſſe vs in thy mercie: that on vs the ſwéete influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of thy ſpirit (with the which thou v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt to grace thine elected children) may be bountifully powred foorth graciouſly encreaſed, &amp; longſomly continued on vs for our perfect inſtruction, for the benefit of thy church, and for thine eternall glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; Teach vs (O father) in the right vſe of thy worde, to know thée the only true God, to know Ieſus Chriſt our ſauiour, and to know our ſelues: that howſoeuer we be ſchooled and catechized by our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily and ſpiritual fathers, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou haſt in thy wiſdome made meanes of our bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter inſtruction, we may be all taught of thée, which giueſt an happy encreaſe to <hi>Pauls</hi> planting, and the Apoſtles watering. Sanctifie vs (O father) that we may be holy, as thou art holy, and confirme vs, that we may be perfect, as thou art perfect: then ſhall we rightly
<pb facs="tcp:14803:48"/>
know thy will and walke in thy wayes: then ſhall we indéed feare thée, and ſerue thée (as we are bound) to holineſſe and righteouſnes before thée, without feare, all the dayes of our life, and finally plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thée, we ſhall enioy that euerlaſting inheritance of thy children in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt felicitie, through the worthy merit of thy moſt deare ſonne our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in whoſe name only wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to come vnto thée, praying as he hath taught vs. <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Our Father which art in heauen. &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions">
            <head>Hereafter follow cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne <hi>godly graces for children to</hi> vſe before and after meat.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Before meate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Moſt gracious God, we beſeech the to ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie and bleſſe all theſe thy creatures, which at this time we ſhall receiue at thy bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hand, giue vs grace (good father) to take and vſe the ſame with right thankfulneſſe to thy wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy glory, and to our comfort, both in body and ſoule, through thy deare ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and ſauiour, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:14803:49"/>
               <head>After meate.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord God our heauenly father, moſt good, gracious, &amp; merciful, we yeeld thee praiſe, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and glory, for theſe and all other thy benefits and bounties powred foorth on vs: and and now we humbly beſeech thee to be mercifull vnto vs, and forgiue vs all out ſinnes, &amp; to grant that thy louing graces and bleſſings may be both encreaſed and continued vnto vs thy high glory and our happy comfort, in Ieſu Chriſt our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Another.</head>
               <p>AS we haue now receiued thoſe thy gifts (O God) whereby we be refreſhed in our bodies ſo grant that the may be alſo ſpiritually fed, and nouriſhed with thy worde, and diuine graces in our ſoules: that ſo both in bodie and ſoule (ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in both the ſweeteneſſe of thy louing mercies) we may prayſe and glorifie thy moſt holy name, through the ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Before Supper.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord, our father celeſtiall,</l>
               <l>Bleſſe vs, and theſe thy creatures all:</l>
               <l>That we may rightly vſe the ſame,</l>
               <l>And therein prayſe thine holy name.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>After Supper.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> Gracious God, we glorifie,</l>
               <l>Thy name, and ſupreame maieſtie:</l>
               <l>For all thy gifts, which from aboue,</l>
               <l>We haue receiued in thy great loue:</l>
               <l>Oh grant vs grace, therefore to be,</l>
               <l>For euer thankefull vnto thee.</l>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:14803:49"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Fol.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">pa.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">lin.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Faultes.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Corrections.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>a</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>courteouſnes</cell>
                     <cell>courteſies</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>b</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>this</cell>
                     <cell>theſe</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6</cell>
                     <cell>a</cell>
                     <cell>7</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8</cell>
                     <cell>a</cell>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>naturall</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſoueraigne</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>b</cell>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſenets</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>ſecrets</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>14</cell>
                     <cell>a</cell>
                     <cell>13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>miniſtery</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>myſtery</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>b</cell>
                     <cell>11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>miniſtery</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>myſtery</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>b</cell>
                     <cell>10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>bleſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Beſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>duty</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>deity</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>16</cell>
                     <cell>b</cell>
                     <cell>29</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>acceſſible</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>inacceſſible</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>22</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>mutable</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>immutable</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
